Finding aid to the Frank G. Carpenter papers SSC.MS.00029
Sophia Smith Collection
Frank G. Carpenter papers
1887-1924
Sophia Smith Collection
Carpenter, Frank G. (Frank George), 1855-1924
SSC.MS.00029
.25 linear feet (1 container)
Frank G. Carpenter was a journalist, author, and travel writer. The collection includes biographical material and letters from 13 women in response to a survey conducted by Frank Carpenter. Topics include women in Congress, women in the military, women and work, marriage, and suffrage. Includes some interesting original correspondence from well-known women's rights leaders.
Biographical / Historical
Frank G. Carpenter, journalist, author, photographer, and world traveler, was born in Mansfield, Ohio in 1855. Following his graduation from the University of Wooster in Ohio in 1877, Carpenter began working for the Cleveland Leader and in 1882 he became the Washington, D.C. correspondent for that newspaper and had a regular column entitled "Carp's Washington." He also wrote for the American Press Association and the New York World. In 1888 and 1889 he financed a trip around the world with his "travel letters" submitted to Cosmopolitan Magazine and twelve syndicated publications.
In 1883 Carpenter married Joanna Condict and they had two children. The family resided in the Washington, D.C. area. After her graduation from Smith College, their daughter Frances Carpenter accompanied her father, as his secretary and photographer, in his travels which continued throughout his career.
Frank Carpenter was a fellow of the National Geographic Society and published many articles and books on geography, some co-authored with Frances Carpenter. Together they also compiled an impressive collection of over 15,000 images (later donated by France Carpenter to the Library of Congress). Frank Carpenter died in 1924 in Nanking, China, during his third trip around the world.
Scope and Contents
The Frank Carpenter papers consist of biographical material and letters from thirteen women in response to a survey conducted by Carpenter. Topics include women in Congress, women in the military, women and work, marriage, and suffrage. The collection also includes some interesting original correspondence from well-known women's rights leaders.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Frances Carpenter Huntington donated her father's papers along with her own papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from in 1965 and 1969.
Related Materials
Frances Carpenter (daughter) Papers, Sophia Smith Collection
Books on famous women donated by Frances Carpenter Huntington to the SSC (some have been transferred to Neilson Library)
The Frank and Frances Carpenter photograph collection, Library of Congress: http://lcweb2.loc.gov/pp/ffcarphtml/ffcarpabt.html
The Frances Carpenter Collection of scrapbooks, Library of Congress
Women's rights--United States--History--Sources; Women--Suffrage--United States-History--Sources; articles; photographs; clippings; correspondence; Books; Carpenter, Frank G. (Frank George), 1855-1924
- SERIES I Survey responses
  - Susan B. Anthony (on women in Congress), 1894-95; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clara Barton, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mabel G. Bell, 1917; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nellie Bly, 1890 undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Maud B. Booth, 1895 undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frances Hodgson Burnett, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jane C. Croly, 1887-93 undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Louisa Drew, 1894 undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hetty Sylvia Green, 1897-1904 undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Isabella (Beecher) Hooker, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miriam Florence Leslie, 1893; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1893-95 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ella Wheeler Wilcox, 1894; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographical information: clipping, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 14)